<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The only rule to walke by guiding Christs ministers, and all his members, how to frame their conuersation in the way to saluation. A sermon preached at a synod, or meeting of ministers in S. Michaels Church in Couentry the second of October. 1615. By S. Gibson, preacher of the word, and pastor in the same city.</title>
            <author>Gibbons, Samuel.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1616</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01698</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11837</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118451</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853658</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853658</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19051</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01698)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19051)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1173:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The only rule to walke by guiding Christs ministers, and all his members, how to frame their conuersation in the way to saluation. A sermon preached at a synod, or meeting of ministers in S. Michaels Church in Couentry the second of October. 1615. By S. Gibson, preacher of the word, and pastor in the same city.</title>
                  <author>Gibbons, Samuel.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by George Purslowe for Ralph Mab, and are to be sold in Pauls Church-yard, at the signe of the Grey-hound,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1616.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>pp. 33-34 bound out of order, before p. [1].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19051:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19051:1"/>
            <p>THE ONLY RVLE to walke by: <hi>Guiding Chriſts Miniſters, and</hi> all his members, how to frame their <hi>conuerſation in the way to ſaluation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Sermon preached at a Synod, or <hi>meeting of Miniſters in S.</hi> Michaels <hi>Church</hi> in Couentry the ſecond of October. 1615.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> S. GIBSON, Preacher of the Word, and Paſtor in the ſame City.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>GAL. 6.16.</hi>
               </bibl> As many as walke according to this rule, peace be on them, and mercy, and vpon the Iſrael of God.</q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>George Purſlowe</hi> for <hi>Ralph Mab,</hi> and are to be ſold in Pauls Church-yard, at the ſigne of the Grey-hound. 1616.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:19051:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19051:2"/>
            <head>To the right VVorſhipfull <hi>Si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> ROBERT COKE, <hi>ſonne and</hi> heire to the right honourable, <hi>Sir</hi> EDVVARD COKE, Lord chiefe Iuſtice of <hi>England,</hi> and to the <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and vertuous Lady, the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy</hi> THEOPHILA<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> COKE <hi>his Wife.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I had reſolued to publiſh this Sermon, which I lately preached to a mixt Audience and thought whoſe name <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſhould vſe in the fore-front fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> protection and countenance of it, I conſidered that to your right Honourable Father I ough<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> moſt duty; who (when I was deiected, for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> loſſe of two noble Lords, both deceaſed in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:19051:3"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:19051:3"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:19051:4"/> ſhort ſpace, which acknowledged me in their life time,) to ſupply that want readily at the firſt motion of a Gentleman, a good friend of mine, accepted of me, and that with ſweete words of ſingular incouragement. Since which time (as by ſpeciall duty I haue beene bound) I haue vſ'd his Honors name, by his permiſſion and allowance, in my publike pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. But fearing, in regard of his ſuperexcel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent worth, and the little value of that which I had now ready to exhibite to him, it might be thought too great preſumption, to preſent ſuch an vnpoliſht piece of worke to his learned eyes, I thought it my beſt way rather to deſcend from the Father to the Sonne; and of all the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, for peculiar reſpects, to ſingle out your ſelfe, with due remembrance of your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Lady.</p>
            <p>It pleaſed God after your happy marriage <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o place you both for a time in that Religious and well-gouern'd City, where I am an vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hy Preacher and Paſtor, and there (your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Father firſt accepting of the Recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſhip, in his loue to the Citie, and in the good opinion he had of the inhabitants for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion)
<pb facs="tcp:19051:4"/> your ſelfe alſo tooke an affection to the people; and their loue being reciprocall to you againe, you ſoone became euen a member of the Corporation, and were elected to be a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament-man <hi>vnanimi conſenſu.</hi> And for the time you there continued, thanks be to God, many had comfort of you: The poore hauing great reliefe at your doore through your Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian bounty, and all ſorts good example by your diligent frequenting of the publique exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes both vpon the Sabaoth and the weeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes. And though my charge lay in another Pariſh, yet it pleaſed you both to take the paines to be partakers alſo of my poore Miniſtry in the other Church. Theſe fruits being found in young beginners, haue giuen good hope of your further progreſſe in the way to life. I haue therefore now taken an occaſion in all duty to be an exhorter vnto you to this end, that ye ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer abate any thing of your loue to GOD and his truth; nor ſuffer your ſelues to bee with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawne from the Chriſtian Faith, which you haue receiued by any ſeducers or bad exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, which abound in this licentious age: But that ye walk on conſtantly &amp; labour to grow in
<pb facs="tcp:19051:5"/> grace, and in the knowledge of our Lord Ieſus; knowing that this will bee your only comfort another day, when all the world ſhall not ſtand you in any ſtead.</p>
            <p>To prouoke you forward heereunto, let me but propound vnto you your Honourable Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers example, whoſe ſteps God and Nature bindeth you moſt to obſerue. In the Faith no man more ſound, making the ſacred Canon of the Scripture the onely rule of his beliefe: and in the exerciſe of his authority, and execution of his great Office, and in the courſe of his life, following the holy rules thereof religiouſly.</p>
            <p>Now as other Ornaments of Art and Nature make him illuſtrious to them that know him, ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t is remarkable, that his religious practices do not any whit eclipſe his reputation, but make him the more to bee magnified in the ſight of good men, aboue others of his ranke. As Schollers and learned men in all Sciences ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour him for thoſe abilities which are moſt in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>equeſt with them, ſo for better things the Church of Chriſt taketh comfort in him, the Tribe of <hi>Leui</hi> bleſſeth him, and the GOD of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eauen crowneth him with multiplicity of his
<pb facs="tcp:19051:5"/> mercies. In the race therefore that you haue to runne (Right Worſhipfull) like a good Sonne, follow a good Fathers ſteps. Now let time be precious with you, &amp; <hi>dum vires anni<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſinunt,</hi> while ſtrength ſerueth, be ſtudious, and induſtriouſly labour for knowledge and true wiſedome. <hi>Remember your Creator in the dayes of your youth;</hi> and ſerue the GOD of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen conſtantly with a perfect heart, that the bleſſings of Wiſedomes right hand and left may be vpon you heere, and that you may find mercy and ſaluation in that great Day; when neither birth, nor blood, nor riches, nor any worldly priuiledge, but onely a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſhall be regarded. And ſo I humbly take my leaue, praying GOD to knit your hearts firmely one to another, and more firmely vnto God, that louing and liuing together in his feare for the time you haue to ſpend in thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> world, you may both be partakers of the grac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of life together in his heauenly Kingdome.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Worſhips euer to bee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded in the Lord, <hi>SAMVEL GIBSON.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:19051:6"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19051:6"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Ood Reader, as hitherto I haue, vpo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> good conſiderations, been baſhful<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> backward to publiſh any thing i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> theſe learned times: ſo neither a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I now growne to any ſetled reſolut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on, to trouble the Preſſe often with my worthleſſe l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bours. But being of late ſomewhat earneſtly ſolic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted, to beſtow one of my Sermons this way; I hau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for ſome competent reſpects condeſcended to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> motion this once: If vpon what reaſons I haue don<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it, any be deſirous to know, I will reueale to him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> part, what in my owne mind I haue oppoſed again<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the diſcouragements occurring. Firſt, my owne d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fects I acknowledge <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and ingenuouſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> without diſſembling, and I am not ſo ſimple but know the maner of many conceited Youths in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> age, raſhly to giue their diſdainfull cenſures, of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> moſt whatſoeuer commeth to their view: yet I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> withall, that euen in theſe times, <hi>ſcribimus i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19051:7"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>octi doctique;</hi> all ſermons that come forth are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot excellent, and though ſome Readers be curious, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>thers are not, and euen printed Tractates are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot without their operation; and therefore who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>noweth whether this (by the bleſsing of God) thogh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> be regardleſs with ſome, may not proue altogether <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ruitleſſe to others? and howſoeuer the enuious and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ainer ſort may hence take aduantage to carpe and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eward mee for my paines, with nothing but words <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f diſgrace, yet I expect better meaſure from bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er men, and conſider withall, that I ſhall hereby <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aue opportunity to gratifie thoſe friends, to whom <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> moſt deſire to giue contentment; and this hath not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>een of leaſt force to animate and embolden mee to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat which I haue done, euen in contempt of arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ancy. I ſee alſo that vnſound members, though of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o credit or worth for learning, haue both tongues <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd pennes againſt the truth; and this hath exci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d me the rather thus to diuulge, what I haue late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſpoken for the truth, in the common cauſe of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hurch and of Religion. Now, if paſsing abroad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hrough many hands, it find approbation amongſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hoſe that be ſound hearted &amp; orthodoxe, I paſſe not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r the raſh and vniuſt iudgement of ſuch, as be ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her contentious or corrrupt, what face ſoeuer they
<pb facs="tcp:19051:7"/> carry. The argument that I haue light vpon, is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry neceſſary for theſe times, of any other: bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent (good Reader) with the ſingle and naked truth, vndeckt with the ornaments of art. The matter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good, beare with the manner; curious and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act diſcourſes I leaue to our rare preachers that come ſeldome into the pulpit. Theſe (I trow) may very wel preach euery time in print; but of vs it is not to be expected, that are exerciſed ſo ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> weekly, through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the yeer: and for my own part, as I can haue but little time vſually for any of my ordinary ſermons, ſo for this, my warning was exceeding ſhort: if I ſhould ſay I had two dayes to prouide for it, I might be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued by ſome that know the contrary, and it fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to my lot altogether vnexpected, it gaue im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediment to all prouident forecaſt. Yet it pleaſed God to giue mee ſome good ſucceſſe in the deliuery of it, and after, no ſmall incouragement from th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> moſt religious and learned hearers then preſent Since which time, I haue peruſed my notes, and hau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> added a little in the margent ſpecially. Of ſome it may be, it will be contemptibly reiected, becauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> vſe ſo many quotations of Scripture, and ſo few of Fathers, and Schoolemen, and other Authors: but am of minde that it were good for theſe that ſet
<pb facs="tcp:19051:8"/> light by diuine authority, in reſpect of humane that they had leſſe learning, and more grace. For my owne part, were my reading and ability ſufficient to do it, I affect no ſuch courſe in the Pulpit as they delight in, as ſauouring too much of the fleſh, and of no vſe to the hearers; if by others that diſtaſte any thing but Engliſh in a Sermon, I be excepted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt for that little liberty I haue taken aboue ſome others, I thinke they alſo are in the extreme, and that a meane betweene both theſe would doe well. Freely to deliuer my iudgement and affection, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching this matter, thus I conceiue as yet: That our maine aime being at the glory of God in the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of his word, and our care to that end not to hinder the vnderſtanding of the illiterate peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le in that which concerneth them to marke: Doubtleſſe a man may lawfully haue ſome reſpect al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o to the learned auditors, when the congregation is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ixt; and now and then vſe a few words in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her language, which they vnderſtand as well as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>imſelfe: and yet I reuerence thoſe worthy Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hers, that vſe to follow their Text and matter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>undly, and ſubſtancially and profitably, though <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hey altogether forbeare what they are well able to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e in this kind. Which way ſoeuer thou inclineſt in
<pb facs="tcp:19051:8"/> thy opinion concerning this point, iudge not me, I iudge not thee. God giue vs all grace, that we may euer ſeeke that, for which chiefly we are ſet on work by our heauenly Maſter, to wit, that tranſgreſſors may bee taught his wayes, and ſinners conuerted vnto him; and, good Christian Reader, pray thou for vs, that the will of the Lord may proſper in our hands.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine in the Lord Ieſus,</hi> Samuel Gibſon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:19051:9"/>
            <head>The chiefe Points handled in this SERMON.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>1.</hi> That we all owe Canonicall obedience vnto God, and are to walke by that rule which he hath giuen vs in his Word.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2.</hi> That the Canon of the Scripture is the only rule of the Church, which Chriſtians are to walke by.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3.</hi> That there ought to be correſpondency in iudgement amongst vs, as well as in affection, ſpecially amongst Teachers.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4</hi> That the liues of Preachers and profeſſors ought to bee anſwerable to their doctrine and profeſſion, and they ought to be examples in all goodneſſe.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The first of theſe points is applied againſt all irregular perſons, that will haue their owne way, and not frame themſelues to doe what God and Chriſt Ieſus requireth of them.</p>
            <p>The ſecond againſt our aduerſaries of the Church of Rome, that magnifie their Church with derogation from the Scripture.</p>
            <p>The third againſt all that hold paradoxes, and affect ſingular opinions, ſome particulars are touched by name.</p>
            <p>The fourth and laſt againſt ſcandalous Preachers, which deliuer good doctrine, and giue bad example to their flocke.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:19051:10"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE</hi> ONELY RVLE to walke by.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PHIL. 3.16.17.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Neuertheleſſe, wherto we haue already attain'd, let vs walk by the ſame rule, let vs mind one thing. Brethren, bee followers together of me, and marke them which walke ſo, as yee haue vs for an enſample.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He words are exhortatory, and the exhortations con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in them are very per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent to the preſent aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly; the former is to <hi>vna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimitie,</hi> the latter to <hi>confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity:</hi> the firſt is not barely <hi>propounded,</hi> but withal the way is <hi>declared,</hi> how we may at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to it. Let vs walk by one rule, that's the way to be of one minde: and whereas the imperfections of ſome, in compariſon
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:19051:11"/> of others, might be a great meanes to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this <hi>vnitie</hi> and <hi>harmony</hi> in iudgement; ſome excelling, ſome being farre ſhort of others in knowledge. Neuertheleſſe, ſaith the Apoſtle, though there bee ſuch diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, and ſome are weake and very defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiue in reſpect of others: yet ſo farre as we haue attained, whether to more or leſſe, let vs <hi>walk orderly</hi> by one <hi>rule</hi> or Canon,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> eſt ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> militare, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tur mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> iuxta ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m ſibi ab <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ratore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xum.</note> which is, the <hi>word</hi> of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>doctrine</hi> of the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,</hi> which teacheth vs to aime at the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God, and the peace of the Church, ſo ſhall we grow to conſent in one, and be of one minde. To this exhortation to vna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimitie or agreement in opinion, he addeth another in the ſeuenteenth verſe, to <hi>confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie,</hi> or imitation of good examples, where he maketh himſelfe the <hi>forme</hi> or <hi>type,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> to which he would haue them <hi>conforme:</hi> yet doth he not propound himſelfe alone for an example, but hee ioyneth others with him,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp;c.</note> whom hee would haue the <hi>Philippians</hi> to <hi>imitate</hi> alſo, wherein they <hi>walked</hi> as hee <hi>walked.</hi> In the firſt exhortation there are diuers things worthy to bee obſerued and conſidered of: of which, I deſire to ſpeake rather profitably then plauſibly.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine </seg>1</label> 1. It is remarkable, that he requireth <hi>wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:19051:11"/> by rule:</hi>
               <note place="margin">That we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Canonica<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bedience God. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and thence we are taught this point, that we are not left to our ſelues, to follow our owne way, and doe what ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth good in our owne eyes, but we haue our <hi>rule</hi> giuen vs of God, which we are to follow conſtantly and religiouſly, neither turning to the right hand nor to the left. <hi>Let vs walke by rule.</hi> From the beginning it hath bin thus. God neuer left man to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to do his owne will, but at the firſt <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> had his <hi>rule</hi> giuen him by liuely voyce,<note place="margin">Gen. 2, 3. &amp; 4.3 Heb. 1.1</note> and after, the Lord declared his will to the fathers in <hi>viſions,</hi> and at length deliuered his mind in <hi>writing:</hi> he gaue his word vnto <hi>Jacob,</hi> his ſtatutes and his iudgements vnto Iſrael, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 147.19.<note place="margin">Pſal. 147.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and that both for their direction in the <hi>worſhip</hi> to be done to himſelfe, and alſo for the well ordering of their <hi>conuerſation,</hi> to his will. Firſt, briefly and ſummarily in two tables,<note place="margin">Deut. 10.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> written with <hi>his owne finger.</hi> Then more largely and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply in other <hi>Propheticall bookes,</hi> where hee hath ſet his people a courſe,<note place="margin">Micah. 6.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and <hi>ſhewed what he requireth of them.</hi> And <hi>curſed</hi> bee hee, ſaith the Lord, <hi>that continueth not in all things written in the law to do them.</hi> Deut. 27.<note place="margin">Deut. 27.</note> And as in the old Teſtament, ſo in the new we haue our rules,<note place="margin">Gal. 3.10.</note> as for the <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:19051:12"/> of God</hi> both <hi>inward</hi> and <hi>outward,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 24 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 10.28 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 6.6 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 11.12 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 21.34 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 6 30. &amp;c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 7.12</note> ſo wee haue our rules alſo of <hi>ſobriety</hi> and <hi>charity,</hi> and <hi>righteouſneſſe</hi> towards men; both toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther make one complete and exact <hi>rule</hi> for the whole catholike Church to walke and order their ſteps after: as the <hi>Iewes</hi> vnder <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſo wee vnder Chriſt are vnder <hi>rule</hi> ſtill; and great reaſon we ſhould be ſo: for <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. hereby almighty God, that <hi>made</hi> vs, and Chriſt that hath <hi>redeemed</hi> vs, exerciſeth his authority and dominion ouer vs, and we, our obedience and ſubiection vnto him; whileſt he giueth vs our <hi>rule,</hi> we yeeld our ſelues to be <hi>ruled</hi> by him, and to do what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer hee commandeth vs, and not what pleaſeth our ſelues. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. It is neceſſary, that a <hi>rule</hi> ſhould be giuen vs of God to walke after, in regard of our naturall blindneſſe and folly, and vnaptneſſe (of our ſelues) to doe that which is right in the ſight of the Lord. We ſee, when in the worſhip of God men haue followed their owne deuices, and not walked by <hi>rule,</hi> in ſtead of honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the moſt high God, they haue <hi>vilified</hi> him with their baſe manner of ſeruing of him; as the Apoſtle ſayth, <hi>Romans</hi> 1.21. <hi>They glorified him not as God:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 1.21.23</note> 1. with wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip ſuteable to his Maieſty, but <hi>turned
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:19051:12"/> the glory of the incorruptible God into the ſimilitude of a corruptible man, and of birds and foure-footed beaſts and creeping things:</hi> and the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> ſwaruing from their <hi>rule,</hi> offended in a high degree,<note place="margin">Exod. 32.10.</note> and <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoked the Lord</hi> to great wrath againſt them with their idolatrous ſeruice: and as in the worſhip of God, ſo in their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation and carriage towards men; all are ſubiect to erre and do amiſſe. It is not in man to <hi>walke,</hi> and to direct his ſteps aright without a <hi>rule:</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, neceſſary it is to haue direction from God, and to follow that, that wee may doe well, and haue comfort of our waies in the end, when we haue <hi>run</hi> our <hi>race</hi> and <hi>finiſhed</hi> our <hi>courſe.</hi> Which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth againſt all vnruly and lawleſſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, ſons of <hi>Belial,</hi> that will not ſubmit themſelues to bee <hi>ruled</hi> by the word of God, but caſt off the <hi>yoke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 2.3.</note> and <hi>rebelliouſly breake out</hi> of all compaſſe, following their owne way which is the way of ſin and errour, as if they were their owne men and had no maſter. Chriſt ſhall be no <hi>Lord</hi> of theirs to appoint them what to do, they hate to be directed and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained by any. I would theſe knew it,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:19051:13"/> that <hi>according to their workes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om. 2.6</note> ſo ſhall it be vnto them in the day of iudgement: <hi>vengeance</hi> ſhall be <hi>rendred</hi> vnto them by Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Theſ. 1.8</note> for their rebellion. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> If they will not be <hi>ruled</hi> by him <hi>here,</hi> they ſhall not bee <hi>ſaued</hi> by him <hi>hereafter.</hi> Others in ſome things are content to follow the <hi>rule</hi> giuen them, but (withall) in other things they will haue their owne way: 1. <hi>In the matter of Gods worſhip;</hi> none more preſumptuous this way then our aduerſaries of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xod. 20.4 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ee popiſh Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ech. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ituled: <hi>The Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n Doctrine,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> manner of a Dialogue, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ween the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er and the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iple. God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eepe the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ren of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ians from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ch maſters.</note> who in euery part will haue their owne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentions, and thereby haue mard all. Our <hi>rule</hi> is, <hi>not to make to our ſelues any grauen image.</hi> But firſt, they haue broken this rule, and then they haue put it out of their <hi>Catechiſmes,</hi> and will not haue it mention'd with the reſt of the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements; great <hi>image-makers,</hi> and <hi>image-worſhippers</hi> they are, after the manner of the heathen they haue <hi>turned the glory of the incorruptible God into the ſimilitude of a corruptible man,</hi> and of birds, picturing God the <hi>Father</hi> like an old man, the <hi>holy Ghoſt</hi> like a <hi>Doue:</hi> vnder<note n="*" place="margin">Nihil f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lſius, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uam licere obis omnia <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cere, que <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eus facit V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n in L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>. 166.</note> pretence of ſuch appearances, &amp; <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> is coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeited as it pleaſeth the <hi>Painter;</hi> and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:19051:13"/> before an image, that goeth vnder the name of Chriſts Image, though nothing like him, they<note n="c" place="margin">Greg. de Va<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lent. Tom. 4. diſp. 1. Gret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerus &amp; alij.</note> teach men to bowe downe and worſhip. I am ſure they haue no <hi>rule</hi> for this, from <hi>God;</hi> but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the contrary:<note n="d" place="margin">Scriptura v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nat, ſic <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> laudat, Feſt. Hom. p. 229. diſp. 37. de imag.</note> in the <hi>Sacrament</hi> alſo they are as audacious, to do co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to the inſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Subſtantial <hi>bread</hi> they haue turned to little round wafers of vnſolid frothy ſtuffe, and <hi>wine</hi> they haue taken from the Lords people,<note n="e" place="margin">Licet Chriſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> inſtituerit ſub utra<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſpecie, &amp; licet in primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiua eccleſia re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciperetur à fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delibus ſub v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſpecie, &amp;c. Concil. Conſt. ſeſs. 13</note> 
               <hi>notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding</hi> the rule of Chriſt, <hi>Drinke ye all of this,</hi> which the <hi>primitiue</hi> and auncient <hi>Churches</hi> conſtantly kept. Thus likewiſe in other things they are a <hi>rule</hi> vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and wil not do <hi>Chriſt</hi> that honor, as to bee directed by him in all things. No, Antichriſt is mounted vp too <hi>high</hi> to ſtoope ſo <hi>low,</hi> as to let Chriſt onely reigne ouer his people. But that proud Vſurper is not got ſo aloft, but hee ſhall bee brought downe low at the length: <hi>whom the Lord ſhall conſume with the ſpirit of his mouth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Theſ. 2.8</note> 
               <hi>and with the brightneſſe of his comming. Euen ſo come, Lord Ieſus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reu. 22.20</note> 
               <hi>come quickly.</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. <hi>In courſe of life:</hi> it is the ſinne alſo of many of our own people, they o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey the Lord IESVS but by halfes:
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:19051:14"/> in ſome things they are content to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him, in other things they will haue their owne way; ſome giuen too much to their <hi>pleaſures,</hi> and to the pampering of the <hi>fleſh,</hi> paſſe beyond the bounds of <hi>ſobrietie:</hi> and others carryed with <hi>paſſion</hi> in caſes of wrong are very <hi>irregular,</hi> and will not be kept within compaſſe, by the good <hi>rules</hi> that our Sauiour hath giuen to all Chriſtians of <hi>patience and meekenes:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 5.39.44 Rom. 12.21 Col. 3.12</note> but ſpecially in things that concerne their <hi>profit:</hi> we ſee many profeſſors break ſquare, though otherwiſe of note for Religion.</p>
            <p>Hence much <hi>falſehood</hi> and <hi>deceit</hi> in bargaining, among thoſe that ſhould giue better example; hence <hi>Vſurie</hi> growne ſo common, though in the<note n="*" place="margin">Exod. 22.25 Leuit. 25.37 Deut. 23.19. Pſal. 15.5 Luke 6.35 Philip. 4.8</note> Word of God there bee much againſt it, nothing for it; and hence <hi>ſacrilegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous withholding</hi> of the goods of the Church from the right owners thereof: but this cannot ſtand with that <hi>integrity</hi> which religion requireth, neither will it ſerue the turne in ſome things to be <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable</hi> and <hi>obedient</hi> to the lawe of Chriſt, but we are to order our ſteppes thereafter in <hi>all</hi> our occaſions. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:19051:14"/> to dra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to a concluſion of this point, let all of vs, as we would be ſure to go the <hi>rig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> way, which <hi>leadeth to life,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.6</note> learne to haue due reſpect to the <hi>Canon</hi> and <hi>rule</hi> giuen vs of God in all things: in the ſeruice and <hi>worſhip</hi> we perform to God; and in our carriage towards all ſorts, whether <hi>ſuperiors</hi> or <hi>inferiors, rich</hi> or <hi>poore, frie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> or <hi>enemies,</hi> in our <hi>words</hi> and in our <hi>w <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kes,</hi> in thoſe things that concerne o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>profit</hi> or <hi>pleaſure,</hi> as well as in other things: in <hi>all things</hi> let vs haue an eye to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>rule</hi> which is giuen vs. For he only walketh <hi>ſafely,</hi> that walketh <hi>by rule,</hi> and hee that <hi>followeth his own way,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay 53.6</note> goeth <hi>out o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the way:</hi> out of the way to <hi>heauen,</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t of the way to <hi>Euerlaſting life.</hi> And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hus much for the firſt point, touching <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he <hi>Canonical obedience</hi> we owe to God.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine </seg>2</label> It is f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rther obſeruable that the holy <hi>Apoſtl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> ſpeaketh not of <hi>rules,</hi> but only of one <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ule,</hi> which hee would haue all to walke by. And thence this doctrine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſeth, that there is but <hi>one rule</hi> onely for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e <hi>whole Church</hi> of Chriſt and all Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſtians to follow: one <hi>rule</hi> of <hi>faith,</hi> ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> one <hi>rule</hi> of <hi>life;</hi> let vs <hi>walke by the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:19051:15"/> ſame rule.</hi> And this point is plentifully ſet forth in <hi>Scripture. To the lawe and to the teſtimonies,</hi> Eſa. 8.20.<note place="margin">Iſay 8.20</note> 
               <hi>They haue Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and the Prophets,</hi> Luk 16.29.<note place="margin">Luke 16.29</note> and <hi>it is written,</hi> ſayth our Sauiour, when he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with <hi>Satan,</hi> Mat. 4.7.<note place="margin">Matth. 4.7</note> and when queſtions were asked him, <hi>What is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, how readest thou?</hi> Luke 10.26.<note place="margin">Luke 10.26</note> and wee may not <hi>preſume aboue that which is written,</hi> 1. Corin. 4.6.<note place="margin">Cor. 4.6.</note> Hence hath the <hi>Scripture</hi> the honourable title of <hi>Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical</hi> appropriated to it: and proper it is thereunto to bee <hi>giuen by inſpiration;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tim. 3.16 Pet. 1.21.</note> &amp; ſo, that alone is the <hi>ſure rule</hi> that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deceiue vs. Neither is there any need of any other <hi>rule,</hi> this is ſo <hi>perfect</hi> and <hi>complete</hi> of it ſelfe, and wil bring the religious follower thereof directly to <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall life,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h. 5.39</note> as 2. Tim. 3.15.<note place="margin">Tim 3.15</note> 
               <hi>It is able to make vs wiſe to ſaluation,</hi> and is <hi>profitable to teach, to improue, to correct, to inſtruct in righteouſnes, that the man of God may be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute and perfect to euery good work.</hi> What vſe then is there of other rules? Let vs <hi>walke by the ſame rule:</hi> and hence let all be warned to take heed of the <hi>falſe and counterfait rules</hi> of our <hi>aduerſaries,</hi> which they haue brought in, to the diſhonour
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:19051:15"/> of the diuine <hi>Canon</hi> and of the author of it.<note place="margin">Regulae mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticae nihil ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ud ſunt, quam ſtultae, &amp; ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes hominum ſuperſtitio for u<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> praeſcriptiones circa res l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cras &amp;c. Feſtus Hom. diſp. 29.</note> Not to ſpeake of their ridiculous <hi>Monaſticall rules,</hi> which ſeuerall <hi>ſectes</hi> keepe ſo preciſely, which are nothing but fooliſh and vaine preſcriptions of <hi>ſuperſtitious</hi> men about <hi>idle</hi> matters, which are <hi>aduerſe</hi> to Gods pure ſeruice and to Chriſtian liberty.</p>
            <p>That which is moſt intolerable is, that they make the Scripture imperfect and defectiue, and ſo but <hi>partialem regulam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bellarm. de verbo D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſcripto c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p. 12.</note> a piece of a rule, and magnifie the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,</hi> and <hi>Councels,</hi> and <hi>Traditions,</hi> and the <hi>Church</hi> ſpecially, and the <hi>Popes</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitiue ſentence <hi>ex cathedra,</hi> making that to bee the maine <hi>infallible rule</hi> of Faith.</p>
            <p>But alas, if wee ſhould harken to them herein, we could neuer be at a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty for our Faith. For 1. As for the <hi>Fathers,</hi> they agree not amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, but are one <hi>oppoſite</hi> to another in many things, and amongſt many <hi>Truths</hi> haue ſome great <hi>Errors. Origen</hi> was an <hi>Allegoriſt;</hi> an vnſound Interpreter. <hi>Tertullian</hi> a<note n="a" place="margin">From who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> he held that prodigious er<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ror againſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond mariag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his argumen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> anſwered by Beza de poly</note> 
               <hi>Montaniſt, Iuſtin Martyr</hi> a<note n="b" place="margin">One that dream'd of a golden worl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to continue 1000. yeeres after the reſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rection, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in Chriſt ſhould reign<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with the Sai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> on earth.</note> 
               <hi>Chiliaſt</hi> or <hi>millenary; Euſebius</hi> halfe an <hi>Arrian.</hi> And others had their ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:19051:16"/> 
               <hi>errors.</hi> And therfore there's no buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vpon them.</p>
            <p n="2">2 As for <hi>Councels,</hi> they were not only ſubiect to erre, but did erre, and of the beſt and moſt eminent of them: as the 1. <hi>Nicen Councel</hi> in a point of<note n="c" place="margin">Canone 19. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, iubent <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; Can. 12 pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ibent eos re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ire ad militia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, qui cingulum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bieciſſent, quod eſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tra Luke 3.14.</note> 
               <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaptiſme,</hi> and another foule <hi>Error</hi> they had like to haue committed, had it not beene for<note n="d" place="margin">Abſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Paph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>anxiſſent, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nini Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>icorum pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſſum eſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ormire cum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xore, quam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um Laicus eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t, duxiſſet, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>elaſ. teſt.</note> 
               <hi>Paphnutius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 As for <hi>Traditions,</hi> they are vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, many of them are <hi>forged</hi> and <hi>coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit,</hi> as our aduerſaries confeſſe.</p>
            <p n="4">4 As for <hi>Popes,</hi> their owne ſtories ſhew, how ſome of them haue been <hi>Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes,</hi> and how they haue croſt one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother. As what <hi>Pope Formoſus</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creede, <hi>Pope Stephen</hi> the ſixt aboliſhed. After, <hi>Iohn</hi> the ninth diſanulled the acts of <hi>Stephen,</hi> and eſtabliſht againe what <hi>Pope Formoſus</hi> had done. After, <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gius</hi> the third diſanulleth what <hi>Formo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> had done, and reeſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed the acts of <hi>Stephen.</hi> Here's <hi>Pope</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Pope,</hi> and one contrary to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: Hee were a wiſe man therefore, that would builde his faith vpon the <hi>Popes</hi> iudgement.</p>
            <p n="5">5 As for the <hi>Church;</hi> the <hi>Catholike
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:19051:16"/> Church</hi> ſometimes is <hi>inuiſible:</hi> and as for any particular <hi>Church,</hi> it is ſubiect to <hi>erre</hi> and <hi>fall away,</hi> as did <hi>Iſrael,</hi> where the chaire of <hi>Moſes</hi> was,<note place="margin">Reuel. 2, &amp; 3</note> and the <hi>Churches</hi> of <hi>Aſia,</hi> to which the <hi>Spirit</hi> ſpake, and <hi>Chriſt</hi> wrote by his ſeruant <hi>Iohn.</hi> And as for the <hi>Romane Church,</hi> there's great dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betweene the <hi>olde,</hi> and the <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 In the Apoſtles time there was no praying in an <hi>vnknowne tongue</hi> there, as now there is, hee flatly condemneth it. 1. Cor. 14.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 14</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 In the Apoſtles time the people were not forbid to <hi>read the ſcriptures,</hi> as now they are: the <hi>Beraeans</hi> are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended for it, Acts 17.11.<note place="margin">Act. 17.11</note> and <hi>Timothy was brought vp in them from a child.</hi> 2. Tim. 3.15.<note place="margin">2. Tim. 3.15</note>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 In the Apoſtles time <hi>Mariage was honourable among all men,</hi> Heb. 13.4.<note place="margin">Heb. 13.4</note> and <hi>Peter</hi> himſelfe had a <hi>wife,</hi> Luke 4.38.<note place="margin">Luke 4.38</note> Math. 8.14.<note place="margin">Math. 8.14</note> But now a <hi>Concubine</hi> is fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for a Prieſt then a <hi>wife:</hi> and diſgrace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully they ſpeake of the Miniſters of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches, becauſe they <hi>marrie;</hi> for which, by the way,<note place="margin">Epiſt. ad O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cean.</note> they may be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, as S. <hi>Ierome</hi> anſwered a diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:19051:17"/> 
               <hi>adulterer</hi> that condemned <hi>Carterius</hi> a married <hi>Biſhop.</hi> For vs it is <hi>written, Mariage is honourable among all men,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 2.18 Reu. 21 8, 9</note> 
               <hi>and the bed vndefiled:</hi> but for them it is added, <hi>whoremongers &amp; adulterers God will iudge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4 In the Apoſtles time they <hi>worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped</hi> none but <hi>God:</hi> now <hi>Angels, Saints, Images.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Cor. 11.25.28</note>5 In the Apoſtles <hi>time</hi> they had the <hi>Communion</hi> in both <hi>kindes,</hi> all the <hi>Lords</hi> people both <hi>eat</hi> and <hi>drunke</hi> at the Lords Table, according to the order appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Lord of the <hi>Sacrament:</hi> now, only a little <hi>w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fer</hi> is pop't by the Prieſt into their mouthes; but to <hi>drinke</hi> of the ſacramentall <hi>cup</hi> they are not allowed. In theſe, and many other things there's great difference betweene the old <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Church</hi> and the <hi>preſent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore it remaineth, that the <hi>ſcripture</hi> is the only ſure <hi>infallible rule</hi> that we can truſt to. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> For 1. There wee are ſure is no <hi>error.</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. There is no <hi>oppoſition,</hi> but a ſweet <hi>harmony</hi> betweene <hi>Moſes</hi> and the <hi>Prophets, Chriſt</hi> and the <hi>Apoſtles.</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. That is euer the ſame <hi>without any alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> though Churches <hi>vary,</hi> that is euer the ſame. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 4. Whereas it may be more
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:19051:17"/> queſtionable, which is the <hi>Church;</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>Greek</hi> or <hi>Latine,</hi> or <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one challe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ging the name. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> That the <hi>ſcripture</hi> is the <hi>Word</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> is out of que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion amongſt vs, and all agree that that conteineth the <hi>Truth,</hi> and nothing but the <hi>Truth.</hi> And therefore, let vs <hi>walke by this rule:</hi> it is wiſdome for vs to make that the onely <hi>rule</hi> of our <hi>faith,</hi> and to cleaue faſt thereunto; it is the ſafeſt courſe to preſerue vs from <hi>error:</hi> and ſo many as walke after this <hi>rule,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 6.16</note> 
               <hi>peace</hi> ſhall <hi>be vpon them, and mercie, and vpon the Iſrael of God.</hi> And hitherto of the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of the Apoſtle tending to vnity.</p>
            <p>Now of the maine exhortation, to vvhich the former vvas but ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, <hi>Bee of one minde,</hi> or,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Minde one thing:</hi> which (as appeareth by the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer verſes) is rather to bee referred to the <hi>iudgement</hi> then to the <hi>affection.</hi> For, he deſired before their conſent in <hi>opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and ſtill hee vrgeth the ſame thing: hee ſawe there was difference amongſt them, &amp; ſome were in an <hi>error,</hi> of whom notwithſtanding he ſpeaketh like him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in the ſpirit of <hi>meeknes</hi> fauourably, charitably, hopefully, <hi>God will reueale:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſe 15</note>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:19051:18"/> yet ſtill calling vpon them to leaue their priuate <hi>opinions,</hi> and to ioine with the <hi>Church</hi> of God in the truth without <hi>op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition</hi> or <hi>diſſent. Be of one mind.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine </seg>3</label> Our leſſon hence is, that thoſe of the ſame faith in Ieſus Chriſt, ſhould labour by all meanes to <hi>agree</hi> in points of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion: as there ſhould be correſponden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy in <hi>affection,</hi> ſo likewiſe agreement in <hi>iudgement</hi> amongſt vs. This he moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly and vehemently perſwadeth the <hi>Philippians</hi> vnto with all ſweet termes of loue, Cap. 2.1. &amp;c. <hi>If there be any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation in Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Philip. 2.1</note> 
               <hi>if any comfort of loue, if any fellowſhip of the ſpirit, if any bowels and mercies, fulfill my ioy, that ye be like minded, hauing the ſame loue, being of one accord, of one minde:</hi> and 1. Cor. 1.10.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Cor. 1.10.</note> There's his moſt earneſt requeſt vnto them for the ſame. The thing there deſired, is <hi>v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,</hi> and it is three-fold, Verball, Reall, and Mentall. 1. In word, <hi>That ye ſpeake one thing.</hi> 2. In deed, <hi>That there bee no diſſenſions amongst you.</hi> 3. In minde, <hi>That you bee knit together in one minde and in one iudgement.</hi> Then marke how affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionately he deſireth it of them. 1. V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing a lowly obſecration, <hi>I beſeech you.</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:19051:18"/> 2. A louing compellation, <hi>Brethren.</hi> 3. An earneſt adiuration, <hi>by the name of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt. I beſeech you bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren by the name of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, that yee ſpeake one thing, and that there bee no diſſentions amongst you; but be you knit together in one mind, and in one iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in his ſecond Epiſtle to the ſame Church, Chapter 13. Verſe 11.<note place="margin">2. Cor. 13.11.</note> when in concluſion he giueth them the <hi>Vale,</hi> hee giueth them a ſpeciall charge for this, to <hi>be of one minde,</hi> and <hi>liue in peace.</hi> All which ſheweth, that it is a matter of great <hi>importance,</hi> that there ſhould bee <hi>concord</hi> in iudgement: and ſure the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary is of dangerous conſequence. For firſt, ſpecially when teachers <hi>differ</hi> in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, it is an occaſion to make vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grounded hearers to <hi>ſtart aſide,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come to bee of no religion. Of olde this turned many from the true faith,<note place="margin">Sozom. lib. 1. cap. 16.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the diſſonancie and diuerſitie of opinions that was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt learned men, was the cauſe that many would not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, embrace the Chriſtian Religion.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:19051:19"/>
            <p>And ſuch pretences at leaſt haue bin made by ſome, that haue forſaken our <hi>Church,</hi> and proued <hi>Romane Proſelytes:</hi> they haue pretended that the hearing of one Preacher, to contrary that which another taught, was the cauſe of their turning. Now, though herein they haue done fooliſhly, not conſidering that this is not <hi>peculiar</hi> to our religion, but hath euer bin in the <hi>Church</hi> of God,<note place="margin">A noble chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge is made them by <hi>D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. White,</hi> p. 154. where he offereth to proue, that there is no point wherein they differ fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs, but they dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues.</note> and that in the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> there is great <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſity</hi> of opinions, as well as in ours; yet <hi>woe</hi> be to them, by whom the <hi>offence</hi> commeth. They haue much to anſwere for, that haue giuen the <hi>occaſion</hi> by their <hi>oppoſite</hi> doctrine. Well, this ſheweth, there had need be great heede how we <hi>differ.</hi> 2. Vpon difference of <hi>iudgement,</hi> ordinarily followeth difference in <hi>affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> and ſo <hi>contention</hi> ariſing betweene the Paſtors, much <hi>miſchiefe</hi> muſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily follow.</p>
            <p>In ancient Churches there haue been <hi>prodigious quarrels</hi> hereupon,<note place="margin">Niceph. lib. 14. cap. 47</note> and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times <hi>murthers</hi> haue been committed, as wee may ſee in <hi>Eccleſiaſticall</hi> Hiſtories. And therefore there had need be great care in euery one to maintaine vnity,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:19051:19"/> and to forbeare <hi>oppoſition.</hi> This then is to be applyed againſt all of what ſort ſo euer, that affect <hi>ſingularity</hi> in opinion, and loue to be in <hi>oppoſitum,</hi> and ſo cauſe <hi>diuiſion</hi> and <hi>contention.</hi> The ſinne of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny yet made a light matter: ſome are of ſuch ſtrange ſpirits, that they make a <hi>tuſh</hi> at the peace of the Church. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the Scripture biddeth vs, not onely <hi>liue in peace,</hi> but <hi>make peace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 13 11 Iames. 3.18 Pſal. 34.14 1. Theſ. 4.11</note> and <hi>follow af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> it, and <hi>ſeeke</hi> and <hi>enſue</hi> it, and <hi>ſtudy to be quiet:</hi> they ſtudy to bee <hi>vnquiet,</hi> and to <hi>diſquiet</hi> themſelues and others. And whereas <hi>Auguſtine</hi> helde the ſinne of <hi>ſciſme</hi> greater then the ſinne of <hi>idolatry,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug de bap. contra Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſtas lib. 2. ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; omnia bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pacis &amp; vni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tis toleranda lib. 6. cap. 22</note> they make nothing of it. Nay, ſome e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen place Religion in making a <hi>breach</hi> and a <hi>rent,</hi> and thinke therefore to bee magnified for their zeale. Sometimes, amongſt the people, wee ſhall ſee ſome that loue to bee <hi>ſingular</hi> (and not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenting themſelues to differ from the Church, in ſuch things as ſome of the grauer and learneder ſort contend a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout) they wil be ſure to haue ſome <hi>trick</hi> by themſelues aboue all the <hi>Ministers</hi> in towne and country, of one ſort or other, and in that they wil be <hi>open</hi> too, that the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:19051:20"/> 
               <hi>congregation</hi> may take <hi>notice</hi> of them: this argueth a great deale of <hi>vanity</hi> in their minds, and is againſt that <hi>modesty</hi> which the <hi>ſcripture</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendeth to <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,</hi> and which is to bee found in men better <hi>ſanctified. Quis ego ſum</hi> (ſayth learned <hi>Zanchius) qui quod tota Eccleſia approbauit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>anch. confeſ.</note> 
               <hi>improbem? Who am I, that I ſhould diſallow that, which the whole Church hath allowed?</hi> A worthy <hi>patterne</hi> of hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>modeſty,</hi> and may make more igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant ones aſhamed of their malepert <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolency.</hi> Againſt this rule of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle it is directly, if men do not their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour, not to diſſent from the Church, but if it be poſſible, to be of one mind. <hi>Be of one mind.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the greateſt blame will lye vpon thoſe <hi>Teachers</hi> that tranſgreſſe this A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolicall <hi>rule,</hi> and with their <hi>Paradox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es</hi> and ſingular opinions trouble our <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> and are inſtruments of euill. I will now deale particularly, onely againſt thoſe that hole and broach <hi>errors,</hi> ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to <hi>Popery</hi> or <hi>prophaneneſſe.</hi> For theſe are the moſt peſtilent members: to ſome the <hi>Pope</hi> is beholding; for they would proue that he is not that <hi>Antichrist,</hi> and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:19051:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> iuſtification by workes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Artie.</hi> 11. Of the iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification of man.</note> is not onely taught in <hi>Rome,</hi> but in the Church of <hi>England</hi> alſo by ſome corrupt <hi>Rabines,</hi> though it bee againſt an article of our Religion. Theſe would either be made <hi>to be of one minde</hi> with our Church, or els it were to bee wiſhed they were ſent to <hi>Rhemes,</hi> or S. <hi>Omers,</hi> or <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alladolyd</hi> in Spaine, or ſome ſuch <hi>peſt-houſe,</hi> which they are fitter for, then to be teachers in <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Others ſpeake diſgracefully of <hi>prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching,</hi> ſpecially of <hi>often preaching.</hi> There is an idle poſition of late ſet on foote, which the <hi>drones</hi> of the Church are very ready to harken to, that forſooth <hi>reading</hi> is <hi>preaching;</hi> I deny not but in a large ſenſe it may bee ſo tearmed, and ſo may <hi>receiuing</hi> the Sacrament alſo, wherein wee <hi>ſhew forth the Lords death till he come,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, 1. Cor. 11.2</note> and as it were <hi>preach</hi> Chriſt crucified thereby. But what ſhould anie goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to <hi>confound</hi> thoſe parts of Gods ſeruice, which the holy Ghoſt and the Church hath euer <hi>distinguiſhed?</hi> In the Scripture, where <hi>preaching</hi> is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of the Miniſter of the Goſpell,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 4.2</note> it is meant hee ſhould <hi>open</hi> and <hi>apply</hi> the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:19051:21"/> Word aright.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an. 45</note> And the <hi>Canon</hi> requiring <hi>preaching</hi> euery Sabboth, requireth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nſwerable to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at, 1. Cor. .3</note> that we <hi>ſincerely diuide the word of truth to the glory of God, and to the best edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of the people,</hi> ſhewing vs that that is meant by <hi>preaching.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the diſgracers of <hi>diligent prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching,</hi> they alſo are againſt the Church in this: for in the Church-booke of <hi>Common-prayer,</hi> as we are appointed to call vpon baptized Chriſtians to <hi>heare Sermons,</hi> as if they could not heare too many:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ollect</hi> on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ers day.</note> ſo in one of the Collects wee pray, <hi>that God would make all Biſhops and Paſtors diligently to preach his holy word;</hi> and that prayer is excellently groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon that triple <hi>paſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> of our <hi>Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our</hi> to <hi>Peter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 21.15</note> John 21.15, 16, 17. <hi>Feed, feede, feede.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thence are wee taught to pray, that thoſe which haue the place of ſpirituall <hi>Shepheards</hi> and <hi>Paſtors</hi> in the Church, may diligently <hi>feede</hi> the flock of Chriſt. But this diligent preaching (they think) would hinder <hi>learned</hi> preaching, and they rather aſcribe <hi>diligence</hi> to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues that come with <hi>elaborate</hi> diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and ſhew much reading, and impute
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:19051:21"/> negligence to them that take leſſe time for a Sermon.</p>
            <p>I anſwere,<note place="margin">Quorum aemu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lari exopto negligentiam, potius qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> rum obſcura<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> diligentiam, vt in prolog. Heauton. Te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> it is better for the poore people that a man preach to them <hi>often</hi> and <hi>plainly,</hi> then <hi>ſeldome</hi> and <hi>obſcurely:</hi> and I am ſure a great deale of paines is taken by ſome to preach <hi>vnprofitably,</hi> and they ſhould haue more comfort in the day of <hi>Christ,</hi> if they would <hi>conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend</hi> more to the capacity of the ſimpler ſort, and ſeeke themſelues <hi>leſſe,</hi> and Gods glory <hi>more,</hi> in the handling of the Scripture. Wherefore, let them not ſcornefully inueigh againſt thoſe that are <hi>profitable</hi> inſtruments in the Church, for that which is rather to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended in them, and wherein they are to be <hi>imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated.</hi> It were more credit for Preachers to bend their ſpeech rather againſt <hi>loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers,</hi> then againſt <hi>religious</hi> and <hi>induſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> men,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 5.17</note> that <hi>labour in the Word and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine</hi> faithfully and fruitfully.</p>
            <p>The laſt moſt impious <hi>paradoxe</hi> that I will now name, is concerning the <hi>Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both:</hi> ſome think the day may be <hi>changed,</hi> and ſome giue out that men may take their <hi>pleaſure,</hi> and haue their paſtimes vpon that day, and the <hi>ſanctifying</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:19051:22"/> is not neceſſary. But where now is <hi>Zanchies</hi> modeſtie? <hi>Quis ego, &amp;c. quis tu?</hi> Who art thou, whoſoeuer thou art, that thou ſhouldeſt preſume to call that into queſtion, which was neuer before called vnto queſtion by any <hi>orthodoxe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vide Sprint of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e Sabb.</note> Church, or Father? With what face dare any ſpeak againſt that, which hath euer been religiouſly obſerued by good men ſince the Apoſtles times vnto ours, and to what <hi>end,</hi> and with what <hi>meaning</hi> is it?<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Sabbath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> great anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ity, Gen. 2 3</note> except to ouerthrow <hi>Religion,</hi> and bring in ignorance, and <hi>Atheiſme?</hi> for from <hi>the beginning</hi> of the world, the hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing of the <hi>Sabbath</hi> hath bin the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holder of <hi>religion</hi> &amp; <hi>godlineſſe,</hi> and once take away the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> and the <hi>ſanctity</hi> thereof, and farewell all ſolemne <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> of God, and neuer looke that <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Religion</hi> can goe forward: giue men but leaue to breake this commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the reſt will be poorely kept: but if no other conſiderations will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile with the <hi>Antiſabbatiſt;</hi> let me put him in mind, that as herein he is againſt the <hi>Catholike Church</hi> in all ages, ſo alſo againſt our owne <hi>Church,</hi> which ſtill vpholdeth the ſanctifying of that day,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:19051:22"/> and to that end appointeth, as all the Commandements to be read continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,<note place="margin">In the booke of Common. Prayer.</note> ſo that Commandement alſo of kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping holy the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> without leauing out one word; and withall hath added a <hi>prayer</hi> for the people, that preſently vpon the hearing of their dutie in that reſpect, they ſhould lift vp their hearts and voices to heauen, that God would <hi>incline their hearts to keep that lawe.</hi> Now what odde dealing is this with the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, when a Miniſter in his lower <hi>pue</hi> ſhall bid them remember to keepe holy the <hi>Sabbath</hi> day, and require their prayer for the ſame purpoſe, and in the <hi>pulpit</hi> teach them that they neede not doe it? here is ſaying and vnſaying, teaching and vnteaching by one and the ſame man.</p>
            <p>Theſe are dangerous errors, and as you ſee, not onely againſt the <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> and againſt the <hi>Truth,</hi> and againſt Gods <hi>ordinance,</hi> and againſt <hi>Religion,</hi> but againſt the <hi>Church</hi> alſo, whereof wee are <hi>members:</hi> that of <hi>iuſtification by vvorkes</hi> is againſt one of the <hi>Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles</hi> of our Religion; that likewiſe of reading, againſt diligent preaching,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:19051:23"/> againſt one of the praiers of the Church, and againſt one of the late <hi>Canons:</hi> that againſt the <hi>Sabbath</hi> is againſt one of the ten Morall <hi>Commandements,</hi> and againſt the Commandement of the <hi>Church,</hi> that appointeth that Law to bee <hi>read</hi> with the reſt; and to be receiued of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple with a ſpeciall <hi>Prayer</hi> for the kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of it.</p>
            <p>Such therefore are not to be ſuffred as maintaine ſuch poynts, but either they are to be <hi>reformed</hi> or made <hi>exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples;</hi> this ſhould be the care of thoſe in authority, that according to the rule of the Apoſtle, wee ſhould <hi>be of one minde.</hi> And thoſe that hold ſingular Opinions, are to be cenſur'd. I ſpeake not this, as if I deſired rigor to bee vſed to euery one that in any thing diſſenteth from the Church. That is not the way to make <hi>peace,</hi> and to make all <hi>of one minde;</hi> it is neceſſary that there be <hi>diſcretion</hi> and <hi>moderation</hi> in gouernment, and a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence put betweene the <hi>errors</hi> held, and the <hi>perſons</hi> that differ, betweene <hi>ſober</hi> men and <hi>turbulent</hi> ſpirits, elſe it may marre all.<note n="*" place="margin">Georg. Caſſ. conſultatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e de relig. ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erdinand. 1. &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aximil. 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>p. cap. de. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ccleſia.</note> 
               <hi>Caſſander</hi> ſpake to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, when he told his great maſters be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:19051:23"/> the Councell of <hi>Trent,</hi> that the chiefe cauſe of the <hi>deſtruction</hi> of the Church in his time,<note place="margin">Nullam eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiae firmam pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſperandam puto, niſi qui Eccleſiaſticae gubernationi praeſunt de ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mio illo rigore aliquid remit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant, ac multo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum piorum votis &amp; moni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis obſequentes manifeſtos a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſus ad regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam diuinariu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> literarum &amp; ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teris eccleſiae, corrigant. haec ille.</note> was to be imputed to them that beeing puft vp with their Eccleſiaſticall power, proudly and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainefully <hi>contemned</hi> and <hi>repelled</hi> thoſe that modeſtly admoniſhed them. And hee was perſwaded <hi>that there would neuer bee firme peace, till they remitted ſomewhat of their extreme rigour and reformed mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt abuſes.</hi> There muſt be <hi>yeelding</hi> euen by thoſe in authoritie, as well as by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, ere there can be <hi>firme concord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But when the <hi>Oppoſition</hi> of any is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudiciall to <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Pietie;</hi> and there is <hi>contumacie too,</hi> then they are not to bee tolerated or fauour'd. Rulers in Church or common-wealth may haue comfort in <hi>ſeuere</hi> proceedings againſt ſuch.<note place="margin">Cal. in 1. cor 11. verſe. 16. Nunquam co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tentionum eri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> finis, ſi certan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> do velis homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem pugnacen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vincere, quia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> centies victus<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> nunquam fat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> gabitur, lege <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiam prude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Caluin</hi> well iudgeth peeuiſh and froward perſons: <hi>Authoritate magis com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſcendos, &amp;c.</hi> ought rather to be ſchoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by Authority, then with <hi>long diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations</hi> to bee confuted; for ſome are of that ſpirit that <hi>centies victi,</hi> as hee ſayth, if they be conuicted an 100 times, they will not yeeld. Some rougher courſe therefore is to be taken with them.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:19051:24"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:19051:24"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:19051:25"/>
            <p>I ſpeake now in ſeaſon of theſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. This is one ſpeciall vſe of <hi>Synods. Nazianzene</hi> ſpake bitterly,<note place="margin">Nazianz. in Epiſt. ad Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>op. Nazian. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Danaeus de po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſtate eccleſiae <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ap. 36.</note> when ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of greater <hi>Synods</hi> then theſe, hee ſayd hee neuer ſaw any good end of them. I will ſuppoſe with <hi>Danaeus,</hi> that he is to be vnderſtood of the <hi>Councels</hi> &amp; <hi>Synods</hi> of his time, when they did all to pleaſe the <hi>Emperor</hi> and the moſt potent <hi>Praelats.</hi> Good vſe (no queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) there is of ſuch meetings of Miniſters, as that thoſe may grow to <hi>knowledge</hi> and <hi>acquaintance</hi> one with another, that bee vnder the ſame <hi>iuriſdiction,</hi> and to maintaine <hi>Loue</hi> and <hi>amitie</hi> amongſt vs, ſo ſpecially to <hi>end</hi> ſuch <hi>controuerſies</hi> as ariſe by any ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring heads, or contentious perſons. If this bee put in practice, no doubt wee ſhall ſee good come of <hi>Synods.</hi> Well, let euery one in his place doe his part that this Apoſtolicall <hi>Rule</hi> may be kept. And we ſpecially that teach others con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, let vs looke that we agree among our ſelues; the way the Apoſtle hath taught vs, <hi>let vs walke by the ſame Rule:</hi> And then,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſal. 133.1.</note> 
               <hi>ecce quam bonum, &amp;c.</hi> a ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſight it is to <hi>GOD</hi> and <hi>men</hi> and <hi>Angels,</hi> when brethren in the Miniſtery
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:19051:25"/> liue together in <hi>vnity,</hi> it is the <hi>ornament</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> and the <hi>honour</hi> of <hi>Religion.</hi> And thus much of the firſt exhortation to <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nanimity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now a little briefely giue me leaue to adde concerning the other part, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it doth much alſo concerne vs. In the next place the holy Apoſtle would haue all to be followers of him, and of ſuch as <hi>walked as he walked.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine </seg>4</label> Where 1. it is to be obſerued, that he taketh it for granted, that as his <hi>Doctrine</hi> was <hi>ſound,</hi> ſo his <hi>example</hi> was alſo <hi>good,</hi> ſo was it with others alſo of the ſame Faith. Whence our leſſon is, that the <hi>life</hi> and <hi>practice</hi> of <hi>teachers</hi> and <hi>profeſſors</hi> ought to be anſwerable to their <hi>doctrine</hi> and <hi>profeſſion:</hi> it is a thing much preſt vpon al Chriſtians,<note place="margin">Ephe. 4.1. Philip. 2.15. 1. Pet. 2.12.</note> that they <hi>walk worthy of their vocation,</hi> Epheſ. 4.1. and that they haue their <hi>conuerſation honeſt and vnreproueable,</hi> 1. Pet. 2.12. and ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally of Miniſters of the Goſpell, wee find it required: <hi>Be thou an example in conuerſation, &amp;c.</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothy,</hi> 1. Tim. 4.12.<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.12.</note> And ſhew thy ſelfe a <hi>pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne of good workes,</hi> to Titus, Chapter 2.7.<note place="margin">Tit. 2.7.</note>
            </p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:19051:26"/>
            <p>And of all Elders this is required, 1. Pet. 5.3.<note place="margin">2. Pet. 5.3</note> to be types or <hi>examples</hi> to the <hi>flocke:</hi> neceſſary this is; becauſe the common ſort look as much, if not more, to a mans <hi>doings</hi> as to his <hi>doctrine,</hi> and to his <hi>practice</hi> as to his <hi>profeſſion.</hi> For they know it is an eaſie matter to <hi>talke</hi> of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe and righteouſneſſe, and to make a <hi>profeſſion</hi> of great matters: but when they ſee a ſhew of zeale and forward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe this way in any, and yet the <hi>life</hi> vngodly, and the practice vniuſt, it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth them conclude, that their <hi>profeſſion</hi> of ſuch ſtrictneſſe is but in <hi>hypocriſie,</hi> and in ſtead of beeing drawne to religious courſes, they are the more <hi>hardned,</hi> and moued the more to abhorre the way of godlineſſe to their owne deſtruction. Though it bee but the ſinne of ſome particular perſons to giue this <hi>ſcandall;</hi> yet from <hi>particulars</hi> the world is apt to conclude a <hi>generall,</hi> and the worſt way euer; becauſe ſome that are forward in religion are <hi>vnreproueable,</hi> and without exception, they will not conceiue that all the forward ſort are good, but if they ſee one do euill, they will conclude per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emptorily they are all <hi>naught,</hi> and there
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:19051:26"/> is no heed to take what any of them ſay or profeſſe. And therefore it is neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, that he that is a <hi>Teacher</hi> of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, be alſo a practiſer of it, and that thoſe that <hi>ſeeme</hi> more holy then others, <hi>liue</hi> without offence, that ſo the <hi>mouthes</hi> of the vngodly may be <hi>ſtopt,</hi> and the <hi>Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell adorned,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tit. 2.10</note> and their <hi>calling approued</hi> to be of God, and ſo they may further the conuerſion of ſoules to Chriſt.</p>
            <p>For this cauſe it concerneth both Preachers and Profeſſors to looke to their liues. The application concerneth all, but my exhortation at this time is ſpecially to my brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the <hi>Ministry,</hi> that they would haue a religious care, that they make not their holy <hi>Doctrine</hi> of none effect by their <hi>miſ-liuing.</hi> As we <hi>teach</hi> godlineſſe and ſobriety, and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne</hi> all exceſſe and vanity, ſo let our <hi>practice</hi> and <hi>example</hi> be anſwerable: let vs neither <hi>deſpiſe</hi> that <hi>holineſſe</hi> in any which wee teach others, nor giue <hi>incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement</hi> to any to do what they ought not to doe, by our <hi>example,</hi> leſt it bee thought that wee vnderſtand not what wee ſay, or that wee <hi>beleeue</hi> not that which wee haue written. Farre be it
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:19051:27"/> from vs to make ſo light of the <hi>Script<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> or of any thing there taught. The word which wee preach, is no <hi>fable,</hi> nor deuice of man, but giuen by <hi>inſpiration</hi> from heauen; and neceſſary it is to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation both for <hi>Preachers</hi> and <hi>Hearers,</hi> to do what is there required, and to eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chew what is there <hi>forbidden.</hi> Nay, God giue vs repentance if <hi>idle words</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede out of our <hi>mouths.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 12.36.</note> For, <hi>of euery idle word men ſhall giue account in the day of Iudgement.</hi> So CHRIST hath taught vs, ſo wee teach others: according let our <hi>example</hi> be, that ſo wee may giue teſtimony of our <hi>Faith,</hi> and of the <hi>reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence</hi> wee beare to euery part of Gods word. This was the holy care of the Apoſtle, as his <hi>doctrine</hi> was pure, ſo his <hi>life</hi> was ſuch, that hee durſt propound himſelfe for a patterne to all Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>Then let not vs be like thoſe <hi>ſtatues</hi> or <hi>poſts</hi> that are in ſome wayes, that <hi>point</hi> the right way to paſſengers, but ſtir not one foot with them; wee muſt not thinke we haue done all that belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth to vs, when we haue <hi>taught</hi> others the way of the Lord; but as good <hi>guides</hi> wee are to go before them, and <hi>leade</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:19051:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> them on the way to <hi>life,</hi> that wee may with our obedient hearers be <hi>rewarded</hi> in the day of CHRST, and be parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of the grace of life together with them. And this is the way to draw <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence</hi> from the people to our perſons, and to make our Miniſtery <hi>fruitfull.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is ſayd, that <hi>Herod</hi> himſelfe <hi>reueren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced</hi> and <hi>feared</hi> IOHN, Mar. 6.20.<note place="margin">Marke 6.20</note> Why was that? Not ſo much becauſe he was a good <hi>Preacher,</hi> as becauſe hee was a good <hi>man.</hi> Herod <hi>feared</hi> Iohn, <hi>knowing that hee was a iuſt man and an holy, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerenced him, &amp;c.</hi> And this made him be more honourd of the people, though <hi>homely attyred,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 3.4</note> then all the Prelates of <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> with all their pompe and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments.</p>
            <p>Whereas if a man preach well &amp; liue ill, it cauſeth contempt of all:<note place="margin">1. Sam. 2.17</note> As <hi>Elies</hi> ſonnes by their wicked courſes made themſelues and the <hi>Lords ſacrifice to bee abhorred.</hi> It is not well done of thoſe that contemne the ordinance of God, for the vnworthineſſe of him that doth the ſeruice: the word is <hi>pure,</hi> though the <hi>preacher</hi> be <hi>impure,</hi> and the <hi>Phariſes ſitting in</hi> Moſes <hi>chaire were to be heard,</hi> and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:19051:10"/> their good Doctrine was to be follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. But few are come to that degree of grace, as to carry themſelues as they ought in this caſe; and therefore we are carefully to looke, that we be <hi>examples</hi> alſo to the people of that wee teach them, that ſo they may haue no ſtumb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling blocke, but that they may reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently <hi>attend</hi> to what the Spirit ſaith in the <hi>word,</hi> and readily <hi>doe</hi> the <hi>will</hi> of the Lord, and <hi>walke</hi> in his <hi>wayes,</hi> vnto their ſaluation. I ſhould in the next place ſhew how good <hi>examples</hi> being giuen, are to be <hi>followed</hi> and <hi>imitated,</hi> that the Apoſtle requireth in this exhortation, <hi>Be followers, &amp;c.</hi> But the time being paſt, I muſt heere breake off. The Lord giue a bleſſing to that which hath been taught.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
